Neda Taherkhani, PhD Linguist, Data Scientist

SUMMARY

Ph.D. in linguistics; researcher recognized for excellence in research with 8+ years' experience in endangered languages data analysis; content developer, leader, and instructor for undergraduate, graduate, and youth camp courses at universities; data science bootcamp student with several group and private projects; an active, creative, and ambitious woman with a diverse background; passionate about exploring new fields and learning new materials; multilingual and multicultural.



Franklin, TN, USA



(516) 241-5681



neda.tahe@gmail.com



linkedin.com/in/nedata



github.com/nedatahe

SELECTED EXPERIENCE

Data Science Bootcamp Apprentice, Nashville Software School, Nashville, USA (2021-2022)

- 9-month, 12-hours-of-a-week, synchronous, online courses
- Applied data science approaches to real-world data using Python, R, and SQL in both group and private projects

Selected private projects:

A morpho-phonological generator for Tati verbs

Built a Python program that generates the underlying-abstract morphological forms for Southern Tati verbs. Used Regular Expressions to generate the pronounced verb forms. I will also use ML to compare results. Information will be provided upon request

Endangered Languages of the world

Built an interactive R Shiny app that represents the distribution of endangered languages of the world



https://github.com/nedatahe/endangered-languages

Elahé Omidyar Postdoctoral Fellow in Endangered Iranian Languages, Stony Brook University, NY, USA (2019-2022)

- Collaborated within faculty members and led students and research groups working on linguistics projects
- Mentored undergraduate and graduate students working on Iranian linguistics projects
- Documented Tati, an endangered Iranian language, by authoring papers on vowel harmony, phonetics, and verb morpho-phonology and initiated a grammar book and a children's story book on it
- Interacted with the administrates within and outside the university about conducting linguistic and cultural research
- Delivered several academic talks about my projects

Research Assistant at Indigenous and Endangered Languages Lab, Purdue University, IN, USA (2014-2019)

- Created content for and trained students on language documentation
- Collaborated with lab mates in producing content and present on Motion Predicates in different languages
- Acted as the language consultant for a field methods and language documentation seminar on various topics about Tati language and

Lecturer of various undergraduate and graduate-level courses, Stony Brook University and Purdue University (2014-2022)

Selected courses taught: Field Methods, Uncommonly Taught Languages, Languages and Life in Iran, Introduction to Linguistics, all levels of Persian language, English for Computer Science

SKILLS

Programming and technical

Python (Regex, Matplotlib, NumPy, Seaborn, Geopandas), R (Shiny, dplyer, ggplot), SQL, Git, ELAN

Languages

English (Near native), Persian/Farsi (Native), Modern Standard Arabic (working knowledge), Southern Tati (native)

EDUCATION

Data Science Apprentice, Nashville Software School(2021-2022)

Data analysis, visualization, and generation through Python, R, SQL, NLP, and Machine Learning.

PhD in Linguistics, Purdue University, IN, USA (2014-2019)

Dissertation: A Syntactic Analysis of Motion Predicates in Southern Tati

Masters in Teaching English (TEFL), Kharzami University, Tehran, Iran (2010-2012)

AWARDS

- Elahé Omidyar Mir-Djalali Postdoctoral Fellowship
- Linguistic Society of America fellowship
- Purdue certificate of excellence in
- Purdue LYNN Awards for Outstanding PhD students